PROFESSOR: OK, let's look at some
step by step examples for
the alpha-beta algorithm.
And just as a reminder, let me
put on the slide the meaning
of alpha and beta.
Alpha is the best already-explored
option along the path to the root for
the maximizer.
And beta is the equivalent for the
minimizer, that is, the best
already-explored option along the path
to the root for the minimizer.
OK, with this intuition in mind, let's
now work through the alpha-beta
execution on this particular
game three.
We start at the top node,
the root of the tree.
This is a maximizer node, so the value
gets initialized to be the worst case
for the maximizer, which
is minus infinity.
And this node will explore
it's children.
We do a left-right traversal,
so first go down here.
So we'll pass out an alpha value and
a beta value, which have these
meetings over here.
Looking at the path to the roof,
this not itself is the root.
In that node, no options have been
explored yet, so along the entire
path, no options have been explored.
So the best available options to
the maximizer is no option.
So that's the worst case minus infinity,
and same for the minimizer,
the worst case, which, for the
minimizer is plus infinity.
Now we're at the first child here.
This is a minimizer node.
So the value gets initialized to the
worst case for minimizer, which is
plus infinity.
It will start looking at its children.
It'll pass down an alpha
value and a beta value.
Alpha and beta have the meanings
shown over here.
So this case, we'll look at
the path to the route.
No options have been explored yet
along the path of the root.
So we still have minus infinity
and plus infinity.
Then we're at the next node here.
This node is a maximizer node.
For maximizer nodes, we initialize
our values to minus infinity.
It'll start exploring its children.
It'll pass down and alpha and a beta
value, again, with the same
meaning over here.
So since no options have been explored
yet, for maximizer or for minimizer,
or we have still minus infinity and
plus infinity being passed down.
This node here's a leaf node.
The value is four.
The value gets passed back up.
This allows this maximizer
node to update its value.
Four is better than minus infinity for
the maximizer, so we have four now.
And before looking at its next children,
this maximizer node decides
where it's even worth it to
look at its next children.
And for that it checks the
following condition.
It checks whether this value of
four, the current value here,
is higher than beta.
If that's the case, then it doesn't
need to look at any
further children here.
Well unfortunately, that's
not the case.
The value v is smaller than beta.
So we still need to look at
the children down here.
OK, so we go down here.
We have an alpha and beta.
Alpha, best option available to
maximizer along the path to the root.
Well, the maximizer now has an
option of four, right here.
So alpha is four.
Beta is the best option
for the minimizer.
No options for the minimizer yet,
so this is still plus infinity.
Get down here, this is a leaf
node, the value is 6.
6 gets passed back up.
For the maximizer, six is better that
four, so the value becomes four.
And that becomes the value
of this node over here.
So six gets passed back up.
The minimizer node looks at the
six and the plus infinity.
Six is better than plus infinity for
to minimizer, so this becomes six.
Now the minimizer considers whether it's
worth going down to look at its
other children.
In this case, just one other child.
To decide this, the minimizer will
compare its current value, v, which is
six, with the best option available
to the maximizer anywhere
higher up in the tree.
Well, the best option available to the
maximizer, anywhere higher up in the
tree-- there is no such options.
It's minus infinity.
In fact, it's stored in
this alpha over here.
So that means we don't get to prune.
We go down here, we have an
alpha and beta value.
Alpha, it's always the best option
for the maximizer along
the path to the root.
Now, here's where it's important that
you look at the phrasing carefully.
It's about the best option along the
path to the route, not the best option
the already has ever
encountered before.
For the maximizer, the algorithm
has already seen a six
and a four over there.
They don't matter, however, because
they're not sitting along the path to
the route from this node.
So alpha is here minus infinity.
Beta, best option for the minimizer
along the path to the root.
Minimizer has an option here, that
option is six, so beta is six.
No we'll get to maximizer
node over here.
Its value gets initialized to be minus
infinity, passing down an alpha and a
beta value.
Alpha is the best option for the
maximizer along the path to the root.
That's minus infinity, because
there's no such option.
Beta is the best value
for to minimizer.
There is one such option, it's six,
so that's a 6 being passed down.
The value of the leaf
node here is seven.
Seven gets passed back up.
Minus infinity gets replaced
with seven because that's
better for the maximizer.
Now the maximizer checks.
Is it still worth checking
my next children?
Well, to verify that, the maximizer
will compare the value that it
currently has, seven, with the best a
minimizer can guarantee, which is six,
the beta value.
That means if the maximizer can get
seven here, the minimizer would never
let that happen.
And wherever that option is available
on the path to the route, the
minimizer will prefer that option over
this option, here, that could lead to
a seven or even worse, because the
maximizer has even more options
available, which we haven't
looked at yet.
Seven bigger than six.
Equivalently, we have the
v bigger than beta.
That means we get to prune.
We don't have to go down this path.
We know that the value of this
node is seven or higher.
We don't know how high, but
it's seven or higher.
It's enough that we know
To pass that back up, we pass
up the seven or higher.
The minimizer compares the seven with
the six, six is better, this was the
last child, so we have
a value of six here.
This six gets passed back up
to the root of the tree.
That's a maximizer between
minus infinity and six.
It'll be for a six, the minus infinity
disappears, we get a six here.
OK, now this node here has to decide
whether it's worth it to explore any
further children.
To do that, it'll check and compare the
current value six with the best
option available to the minimizer
anywhere higher up in the tree.
Well, minimizer has no options
higher up in the tree.
So that's no reason for the minimizer
to deviate from getting here-- no
option to do so.
So we still need to go down.
The alpha value here is the best option
for the maximizer so far.
The best option for the maximizer
is to go down this path and
would attend a six.
Beta is the best option for the
minimizer, no options for the
minimizer yet, so that's
plus infinity.
Now we're at a minimizer node.
We'll initialize with plus infinity.
Then it'll look at its first child.
It'll pass down an alpha and a beta,
same meaning as they've always had,
best option is available along
the path to the root
for each of the players.
For alpha, that's six, for beta that's
still plus infinity because no past
have been explored for the minimizer
along the path to the root.
Now we're at this node here.
We initialize the value
to minus infinity.
That's the worst case
for the maximizer.
And we start exploring its first child,
passing down an alpha and a
beta value.
Alpha fills six here.
Beta plus infinity, then
look at this node.
The value of leaf node is one.
The one gets passed back up.
The maximizer says one is better than
what I currently had, so I replace
minus infinity with one.
Now the question is, do I still need
to explore any remaining children?
To decide that what the maximizer does,
it compares its current value,
one, with options already available
to minimizer anywhere along
the path to the route.
There are no such option for the
minimizer, so there is no such
possibility of pruning here.
So we have to go down this path here.
We pass down a alpha value
and a beta value.
Alpha is the best option
for the maximizer.
The maximizer had a six and has a one.
Among those two six is best,
alpha a six, beta is best
option for the minimizer.
Along the path to the root, well, no
options have been explored yet.
So still plus infinity.
Coming down here, we see two,
we pass the two back up.
We compare the two with the one.
Well, two is better than one,
so the value here is two.
The two gets passed up to
this minimizer node.
Two is better than plus infinity for
the minimizer, so we make this two.
Now we need to contemplate whether we
need to still explore other children
of the minimizer.
To decide on this, we look at the
current value for the minimizer, here,
which is two.
We compare with the best option
available to the maximizer, which is
stored in alpha, which is
sitting right here.
And we have six.
Well, the maximizer has a better
option available than two--
six.
The minimizer here has an option to
force a two, and then has other
options for which we don't know
yet what the value will be.
But we do know the minimizer could
potentially force a two.
And if it's going to take another option
than the two, it's going to be
even worse for the maximizer.
That means the maximizer would never
let the game get down here because
that two is worse than the six it could
guarantee by veering the game
off to the left.
So we don't have to look at this part of
the tree because no matter what the
values are there, all it can do is
make the value of this node here
smaller than two.
Whatever value is smaller than
two, doesn't matter.
Two or smaller always means
the maximizer would
never take this option.
So we have a value here smaller than
or equal to two for the node.
We pass back up the two.
The maximizer compares that two with
the six it has, and it says,
well, six is better.
So I retain my value of six.
The maximizer then, again,
has to make a decision.
Is it worth exploring
any next children.
To make that decision, it compares it's
current value, which is six, with
the best option available to the
minimizer on the path to the root.
But that path to the root is empty.
There are no such options
for the minimizer.
So I have to go down this path.
Passing down alpha and beta, try the
best options available for a maximizer
or minimizer along the
path to the root.
Well, maximizer at the route
as an option of six.
That's the only option, so
it's the best option.
The minimizer has no options.
So we have plus infinity here.
We'll look at this node here.
This is a minimizer node.
We visualize its value
to plus infinity.
And it'll look at first child.
We'll pass down an alpha
and a beta value.
Alpha is, again, best option for the
maximizer along the path to the
root, that's 6.
Beta, similarly, for the minimizer,
that's plus infinity.
This node initializes
itself to maximizer,
initializes to minus infinity.
It'll look at his first child.
First child get passed an
alpha and a beta value.
The values are six and plus infinity.
That child is a leaf node, so just
pass that value back up.
The maximizer prefers eight
over minus infinity.
So the current estimate is eight.
Now, before it starts looking at its
next children, it has to decide
whether that's even needed.
It will compare eight with the best
option the minimizer could potentially
force higher up in the tree.
So we look higher up in the tree.
No options have been explored for the
minimizer yet, so no pruning.
Equivalently, we compare that eight with
beta, which is the best option
available to the minimizer
higher up in the tree.
Beta is plus infinity.
So eight is a lower value,
so no pruning.
We go down this path.
Pass down an alpha and beta, alpha is
the best option for the maximizer,
which is now eight, which is
obtained by going here.
And for the minimizer, best
option is still no options
available, so plus infinity.
We have a value of one.
Pass the one back up to
an eight and one.
Eight is the better one, so we
retain eight and the value of
this node is eight.
We pass the eight back up for here.
The minimizer compares eight
with plus infinity.
Eight is better.
So the current value is eight.
Then the minimizer decides whether or
not it's worth going down to look at
its next children.
It looks at its value, eight.
It compares it with options
available to the maximizer
higher up in the tree.
The best options available to the
maximizer higher up in the tree is
alpha, which is six.
Eight is better than six, so
the maximizer might let the
game come over here.
So we need to explore what exactly
the value is over here.
So we go down, look at the next
child of the minimizer.
Alpha is best option for the maximizer
on the path to the root.
So that's six here.
And beta is the best value available
to the minimizer on the path to the
root, and that's eight.
Coming to this maximizer node
here, initializing its
value to minus infinity.
Look at its first child, passing
down an alpha value of six, a
beta value of eight.
Eight's child here is a leaf
node with a value of nine.
So nine gets passed back up.
The maximizer prefers nine
over minus infinity.
So we have nine here for now.
Then to decide whether or not it's worth
going down this path here, the
maximizer has to look at what the
minimizer has available to itself.
Well, on the path of the root, the
minimize had an option of eight.
Namely over here, if the minimizer had
gone to the left, the value of the
game would be eight.
Since the maximizer here is able to
achieve nine, and maybe higher, thanks
to unexplored options, which could
only increase the value for the
maximizer, or minimizer would veer off
to the eight, rather than letting it
get to a place where the maximizer could
get nine or maybe even better
for the maximizer.
So we don't need to consider
what's down here.
This can be pruned.
We know that value of this node for
the maximizer is at least nine.
We know enough.
We pass up the nine.
The minimizer retains the eight, eight
is better than nine for the minimizer.
Then this eight gets passed back up.
The maximizer at the top
compares eight and six.
Eight is better.
And so we have here, the value
of the game to be eight.
And that's it.